### IR. DR. PRAJINDRA SANKAR KRISHNAN

Senior Lecturer in Electrical Engineering | Data Analytics | Renewable Energy | Al Research



#### **SUMMARY**

I am a Senior Lecturer with extensive experience in teaching and coordinating various engineering courses, specializing in LMS development and blended learning integration. My professional journey is marked by significant academic achievements, professional certifications, and a track record of contributing to educational and consultancy projects. I have played pivotal roles in curriculum development and stakeholder engagement, demonstrating leadership in both academic and professional services, all driven by a lifelong commitment to technological advancement and education

#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Institute of Sustainable Energy Core Researcher - HICoE

#### **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

- · Perovskite solar cell fabrication training at Ritsumeikan University, Kyoto, Japan with 15% efficiency
- · Contributed in Higher Institution Centers of Excellence (HICoE) audit ensuring compliance with standards
- Site inspection at QL Aquamarine Sdn. Bhd., shrimp farming (Sabah, Malaysia) for Solar Powered IoT sensors installation

#### Course Coordinator/Developer/Moderator

#### **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

- Developed LMS learning content incorporated with Blended Learning level 3 (Flipped Classroom) and level 4 (adaptive learning) for:
- Data Analytics for Engineers
- Elements of Industrial Revolution
- Advanced Artificial Intelligence Masters Program (Moderator)
- Artificial Intelligence and Neural-fuzzy Systems (Moderator)
- Data Communication and Network (Moderator)
- Introduction to Emerging Technologies/Introduction to E & E Engineering
- Microprocessor Systems & Microprocessor Systems Lab
- Electronic Analysis & Design
- Digital Logic Design

#### Head of Unit (Stakeholder Relations)

#### **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

- Improved stakeholder engagement at Universiti Tenaga Nasional by:
- Organizing 6 Industry Advisory Panel (IAP) meetings
- Organizing 8 industrial talks for undergraduates
- Captured IAP feedback for BEEE program curriculum enhancements
- Arranged 2 Staff-Student meetings to get students feedback on teaching standards and facilities
- Arranged 2 Alumni-Staff meetings to get alumni feedback on curriculum improvement based on current industry demands

#### External Examiner for Research Projects

#### **International Medical University Malaysia**

 Evaluated 6 research projects in Master in Healthcare Informatics & Analytics and 1 research project in Bachelor in Medical Sciences program

#### **External Examiner for Coursework**

#### **Perdana University**

**m** 01/2022 - 01/2022 Malaysia

• Evaluated 1 MSc Bioinformatics program student

#### PhD Supervisory Team

#### **Universiti Putra Malaysia**

• Supervised 1 PhD foreign student at Universiti Putra Malaysia, resulting in 1 published research papers and 2 journals submitted

#### **KEY ACHIEVEMENTS**

#### **Academic Leadership**

Coordination and leadership roles in educational programs, resulting in improved curriculum development and stakeholder engagement (Industry Advisory Panel)



#### **Certified Professional**

Recipient of multiple professional certifications in cybersecurity, data science, and IoT development through intensive training programs with recognized institutions



#### **Teaching Impact**

Instructed over 6000 undergraduate students, supervised 95 FYP students, 52 internship supervisions, 6 masters and 3 PhD postgraduates supervision (main supervisor for 5 postgraduates)



#### **Research Publication**

Published 39 peer-reviewed papers, books and technical reports. Scopus h-index: 6 with 119 citations and 13 ISI papers



#### **Project Leadership**

Led and successfully closed 9 research grant projects worth RM 2.2 mil

#### **LANGUAGES**

<b>English</b> Native	••••
<b>Malay</b> Proficient	••••
Tamil Intermediate	••••

#### **SKILLS**



#### **EXPERIENCE**

#### **Guest Lecturer**

#### **University of Nottingham Malaysia**

**m** 03/2020 - 05/2020

- Malaysia
- Contemporary Engineering Themes EEEE2048 (Internet of Things)
- Delivered technical presentation on IoT framework with hands-on activities and evaluated coursework reports

#### Electrical & Electronics Dept. Lab Manager

#### **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

苗 2016 - 2021 👂 Malaysia

- Upgraded 10 undergraduate laboratories with projectors, smart screens, measurement instruments, 3D printer and kits to enhance students learning

#### Journal Reviewer

#### **Elsevier**

**===** 11/2020 - 10/2024

- Malaysia
- 5 reviews for Engineering Applications of Artificial Intelligence
- 2 reviews for Knowledge-Based Systems

#### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD in Electrical Engineering by Research Graduate Program

#### **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

**=** 01/2014 - 01/2018

- Malaysia
- Developed a new optimization algorithm with enhanced exploration and exploitation capabilities for optimized beam forming in wireless communication application
- · Coding and simulation done in MATLAB

#### Master's Degree in Electrical Engineering by Research Graduate Program **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

**=** 01/2007 - 01/2009

- Malaysia
- · Developed Genetic Algorithm code for embedded system for WCDMA adaptive beam forming
- Coding done in C and MATLAB

#### Bachelor's degree in Electrical and Electronics Engineering (Honors)

#### **Universiti Tenaga Nasional**

#### Diploma in Electrical and Electronics Engineering

#### **Ungku Omar Polytechnic**

#### **CERTIFICATION**

#### Remote Pilot Certification of Competency-Basic (RCoC-B)

Remote Pilot Certification of Competency-Basic (RCoC-B) awarded by SG Academy, Asia Drone Technical Academy

#### **Certified Cybersecurity Specialist**

Certified Cyber Security Specialist awarded by iTrain Asia Sdn.Bhd

#### **Certified Python Programmer for Data Science**

Certified Python Programmer for Data Science awarded by iTrain Asia Sdn.Bhd

#### **Industrial Internet of Things (IIoT) Developer**

Industrial Internet of Things (IIoT) Developer awarded by Perak Human Capital **Development Centre** 

#### **Android Certified Associate Developer**

Android Certified Associate Developer awarded by iTrain Asia Sdn.Bhd

#### **Professional Certification in Big Data and Analytics**

Professional Certification in Big Data and Analytics awarded by Innodatatics Sdn.Bhd

#### **Microsoft Certified Systems Administrator**

Awarded by Info Trek - Microsoft Gold Certified Partner and EC Council Accredited Training Center

#### **Java Programming**

Awarded by Oracle University

#### PROJECTS/RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

#### Cost-Efficiency Enhancement of Large Scale Solar (LSS) Farms By Artificial Intelligence Based Forecasting Mechanism & Fault Detection

**m** 2022 - 2024

Malaysia

A project aimed to enable quick analysis of new LSS based on GPS location and predict yield generation. Funder: TNB Seeding Fund

- Developed GUI with new LSS analysis, existing LSS prediction model with degradation factor increasing energy yield by 3-5% and reducing maintenance costs by up to 15%
- Skills: VB.Net, Python, LSTM, XGBoost, PID, Thermal drone

#### Al Framework for Threat Assessment and Containment for COVID-19

苗 2022 - 2024 👂 Malaysia, Sri Lanka

Al framework for COVID-19 threat assessment and containment. Funder: IDRC Canada

- · Developed a contract tracing software using AI for policy-making with a focus on women, children, and underprivileged groups
- Skills: VB.Net, SQL, Android, HDBSCAN, Markov chain, Database structure, cluster computing

#### RE Demand Forecasting and Load Estimation for NEM Customers Using Machine Learning and Data **Analytics**

**=** 2022 - 2024

Malaysia

A project aimed at improving solar generation forecasting using data analytics. Funder: TNB Seeding Fund

- · Developed GUI for solar generation forecasting for NEM customers using Machine Learning with 20% improvement in prediction accuracy
- Skills: VB.Net, SQL, LSTM, HDBSCAN

#### Simulation-Based Machine Learning Predictive Models in Power Transformer Systems Fault Diagnostics

Created a predictive model for fault detection in power transformers using AI

- · Developed an algorithm for transformer failure root cause analysis
- Skills: Machine Learning, Al, Predictive Analytics, Substation Monitoring

#### Mobile Application Worksheet for Undergraduate Lab Experiment with User Input Interface

A project aimed to create a paperless lab worksheet

- Filed one copyright under 'Artistic' category with the title, "e-Worksheet for Undergraduate Lab Experiment"
- Skills: MIT App Inventor, mobile app APK

#### Feasibility Investigation of an IoT Architecture with Machine-to-Machine (M2M) Interworking Framework for Energy System Prognostics

**#** 2018 - 2019

Malavsia

Developed an IoT-based framework for energy system monitoring and prognostics

- Integrated Keras and Raspberry Pi for real-time wireless sensor data analysis
- Skills: IoT, Machine Learning, Keras, Raspberry Pi, Sensor Networks

#### Circuit Design of Handheld Body Iron Store Reader Prototype

**=** 2017 - 2018

Malaysia

Designed a microcontroller-based portable iron reader with a micro cuvette.

- Developed a hardware prototype for low-cost iron deficiency detection (won GOLD award in innovation)
- Skills: Embedded Systems, Microcontrollers, **Biomedical**

#### **CONSULTANCY PROJECTS**

and AI Methods

#### 11

### Software Enhancement and Knowledge Transfer for T-PEMS During Relative Accuracy Audit (RAA)

**#** 2024 - 2024

Conducted software enhancement and knowledge transfer for T-PEMS at Sultan Ibrahim Power Plant (SIPP), Pasir Gudang and Tunku Jaafar Power Station (TJPS), Port Dickson. Optimized sensor calibration algorithms, reducing measurement errors by 10% and ensuring higher data reliability.



## Development of Low Intelligent Network System (LINES) For Predictive Maintenance and Non-Technical Loss Detection

**===** 2021 - 2023

Developed a data analytics platform to detect electricity fraud & non-technical losses (NTL) across 9 million smart meters. Designed 10+ machine learning algorithms, integrated Python, MSSQL, InfluxDB, and Grafana for real-time analytics, reducing fraud investigation time by 30% and improving fraud detection efficiency by 5%



**#** 2020 - 2022

Developed PEMS RATA testing model for gas turbine emission monitoring using artificial intelligence and data analytics. Built a predictive emission model with an accuracy of 95%, ensuring compliance with Department of Environment (DOE) regulations.

**=** 2019 - 2021



#### Development of Smart Billing Data Development Architecture and Software Toolset (SBAST) for TNB Advanced Metered Customers

Designed the LINES analytics system in TNB Datalake for grid failure prediction & fraud detection, analyzing 50,000+smart meters. Developed 8 Al fraud detection algorithms, GIS-based Breakdown Area Mapping (BAM) for outage visualization, and Worst Performing Feeder (WPF) analytics, reducing non-technical losses by 10% and enhancing grid reliability

**#** 2018 - 2019

#### Research and Development of Advanced Portable Surveillance Camera with Intrusion Alert System

Developed video management system (VMS) with motion detection and camera module design for intrusion detection. Created a compact and portable surveillance unit, reducing hardware costs by 30% compared to conventional solutions. Implemented real-time alerts, improving response time to intrusions by 60%.

**=** 2017 - 2018

# Development of Faults Classification System for TNB Distribution Switchgear Based on Ultrasound Analysis Using Extreme Learning Machine (ELM)

Developed sound feature extraction system for TNB switchgear fault classification, enhancing predictive maintenance strategies. Implemented time-domain and frequency-domain sound analysis, improving maintenance scheduling efficiency by 35%.

**= 2016 - 2017** 

#### R&D of Intelligent Abnormality and Fraud Analytic System (AFAS) for TNB Ordinary Power Customers

Developed pseudo codes for fraud detection algorithms and identified fraud patterns from load profiles, enhancing fraud prevention strategies. Built Al-powered fraud detection system, increasing fraud case identification from 60% to 85%

#### PROFESSIONAL BODIES

Institute of Engineers Malaysia (IEM) Corporate Member 苗 2018 - Present

Professional Engineer (Ir.)

📅 🛮 IEM Member

**#** 2013 - 2018

Graduate member



苗 2009 - Present

Boards of Engineers Malaysia (BEM)

苗 2010 - Present

Registered member

#### PROJECTS/RESEARCH ACTIVITIES

Wideband Transmit Beamforming Optimization using a New Dynamic Socio-Spatial Behavior Algorithm for Planar Phased Array with Antenna Switching

Developed an Al-based optimization model for beamforming applications

- Designed an optimization algorithm improving beamforming efficiency (PhD work)
- Skills: Al, Optimization, MATLAB, Phased Array Antennas

#### IEEE 802.16 (WiMAX) Teletraffic Performance Improvement by Innovative Smart Antenna System

🗰 2013 - 2015 👂 Malaysia, India

Designed a pseudo-smart antenna system improving WiMAX teletraffic performance

- Developed a signal processing algorithm for adaptive beamforming
- Skills: Wireless Communication, Smart Antennas, Signal Processing

## Vaccine-Enhanced Artificial Immune System for Multi-Criteria Optimization Algorithm

Developed a new multi-objective optimization algorithm based on artificial immune system principles

- Applied bio-inspired computing to enhance decisionmaking efficiency for industrial application
- · Skills: Al, Optimization, Bio-Inspired Computing

#### Analysis of Artificial Clonal Selection and Hypermutation on Genetic Evolutionary Computation

Designed a hybrid AI algorithm combining clonal selection and evolutionary computation

- 2 journal published
- Skills: Genetic Algorithms, Evolutionary Computation,

#### **FIND ME ONLINE**



https://prajindra.github.io/myprofile/

My Web Profile

n htl

https://www.linkedin.com/in/prajindra/

Linkedin Profile



https://www.youtube.com/@prajindrasankar5879

YouTube channel